1965 年是美国历史上发生重大变化的一年
1965 was a year of massive change in America.
《民权法案》就是在那年签署的
The Civil Rights Act was signed.
Congress passes the most sweeping civil rights bill ever to be written into the law.
“…国会通过了史上影响最为广泛的《民权法案》”
“并将它写进了法律里…”
作战部队被第一次被派往越南
Combat troops were sent to Vietnam for the first time.
Ways against North Vietnamese party.
“…对抗北越的方式…”
男人们烧掉了他们的征兵证
Men burned their draft cards.
Draft cards on the steps of a Boston courthouse.
“…征兵证被放在波士顿法院的台阶上”
A group of high school boys set upon them with fists.
“一群高中男生挥拳猛捶它们…”
在纽约 披头士乐队举行了世界上第一场体育馆内的音乐会
The Beatles delivered the world's first stadium concert in New York.
但在距离这些大新闻很远的地方 一场与众不同的革命正在酝酿
But, far from all those headlines, a revolution of a different kind was underway.
5 月 1 号 凌晨 4 点
4:00 AM, May 1st.
约翰·凯梅尼教授和一名本科生
Professor John Kemeny and an undergrad student
正在达特茅斯的 GE 225 型电脑上忙碌着
were working at a GE 225 computer at Dartmouth University.
他们运行了一个刚写好的程序
They ran a program they'd been working on.
电传打字机的三行输出
And then the teletypewriter produced three short lines of output.
永远地改变了计算机编程领域
Those three lines changed computer programming forever.
欢迎来到红帽原创播客《代码英雄》的第 3 季第 2 集
Welcome to episode 2 of Command Line Heroes, an original podcast from Red Hat.
我是主持人 Saron Yitbarek
I'm your host, Saron Yitbarek.
在这一集 我们将继续本季的“编程语言的过去与未来”的旅程
In this episode, we continue our season-long journey into the history and future of programming languages.
在第 1 集中 我们深入研究了 Python
In episode 1, we dove into Python
并了解了开源社区如何在其领导阶层的大动荡中生存下来
and learned how open-source language communities
survive major upheavals in their leadership.
比起上一期节目 本次节目会更注重于个人
But this time, we're getting more personal.
我们的话题是 大家都有过的一种体验
We're looking at an experience we've all had.
也就是 与入门语言的邂逅
The experience of encountering our very first language.
我将带领你们领略我学习的第一门语言 Ruby
We'll take a look at my first language, Ruby.
以及新手语言是如何用游戏的形式 来到我们身边的
And we'll learn how some first languages come to us in the form of a game.
不过 我得先举个例子
But we're beginning with an example
好让大家都能明白“新手语言”到底是什么意思
that can help us understand what first languages really means.
这门语言诞生于
It's the language that was born
之前提到的 达特茅斯实验室的三行输出
in that Dartmouth laboratory with those three short lines of output.
在 1965 年那一天的黎明之前
At that pre-dawn meeting in 1965,
约翰·凯梅尼作为创造者之一 见证了 BASIC 的诞生
John Kemeny witnessed the birth of his co-creation, BASIC.
BASIC 的意思是“初学者的泛用符号指令代码”
BASIC.
It stands for Beginners' All-Purpose Symbolic Instruction Code.
这里面的第一个词 “初学者” 正是其不凡之处所在
In that first word, "beginners'", is where the magic lies.
在早期
In the early days of programming,
就算是少量的编程工作 也需要一名博士来完成
you pretty much needed a PhD in order to do a little coding.
这是一种极高的要求 需要大量的教育
It was an elite pursuit that required major education, not to mention major hardware.
更不用说那些高级的硬件了
但是凯梅尼教授和他的团队希望改变现状
But Professor Kemeny and his team wanted to change all that.
他们想知道：如果要创造一种所有人都可以使用的编程语言
What would it look like, they wondered, to produce a programming language that anybody could use?
那会带来怎样的不同？
当美国各地的青年们剧烈地抗议 要求变革时
While teenage baby boomers were demanding change all across America
达特茅斯团队提出了一种另类的革命
the team at Dartmouth proposed a shake-up of another kind.
他们的秘密武器是一个房间那么大的大型电脑 - GE 225
Their secret weapon was a room-sized mainframe computer, that GE-225
它重达 2000 磅 这个重量是健康的证明
weighing in at a healthy 2,000 pounds, it was capable of something brand new.
2000 磅大约是 900 千克
和这份不得了的重量相匹配的是 它具备某些全新的功能
weighing in at a healthy 2,000 pounds, it was capable of something brand new.
那就是分时功能
The GE-225 was capable of time-sharing.
也就是时间片 实现了多用户多进程快速切换的技术
突然间 编程不再需要复杂的打孔卡系统或庞大的开关墙了
Suddenly, the complicated system of punch cards or enormous walls of switches wasn't necessary anymore.
分时意味着程序们都可以同时执行
Time-sharing meant that a whole bunch of programs could be executed almost simultaneously
因为系统会根据不同用户的需要来回切换其处理内容
with the machine's attention bouncing between users.
分时意味着 使用者可以用惊人的新方式来访问计算机
Time-sharing meant that access to computing could expand in amazing new ways.
这是来自达特茅斯的些许录音
Here's some audio from Dartmouth,
记录了 BASIC 刚诞生的时候
featuring one of the undergrads studying there when BASIC first appeared.
65 级的本科生 John McGeachie 学习的实况
Here's John McGeachie, class of '65.
我们把这台相当贵的、原本只能一次让一个人用的计算机
We had taken a fairly expensive computer that could only be used by one person at a time
变成了可以…让超过 30 人使用的东西
and converted it into something where it wasn't just 30 users who could use it
30 名本科生可以同时在这上面编程
it was 30 undergraduate students using this computer simultaneously
还能快速得到输出
writing programs, getting answers quickly.
它是史无前例的简洁直接
It was a combination of immediacy and simplicity that had not previously existed.
约翰·凯梅尼联合另一位技术普及的布道师托马斯·卡茨
John Kemeny had teamed up with Thomas Kurtz, another evangelist for computer literacy
共同开发了 BASIC 语言
to develop the BASIC language.
他们发现 分时让计算机使用变得更亲民
They saw how time-sharing democratized things,
因此准入门槛降低了许多
and knew that the barrier for entry was suddenly so much lower.
而剩下的工作则是编写一门简单直白的编程语言
All that was needed was a language that prioritized simplicity and immediacy,
一门像 BASIC 那样的语言
a language like BASIC.
他们开发了像 HELLO 和 GOODBYE 这样的指令
They developed commands like "hello" and "goodbye" instead of "log on" and "log off".
来代替 LOG ON 和 LOG OFF 命令
事实上 初版 BASIC 只有 14 个简单的指令
In fact, the first version of BASIC only had 14 simple commands,
比如条件判断 IF 和 GOTO 之类的简单选项
just easy options like "if", "then", and "go to".
我是 Tom Cormen
I am Tom Cormen. I'm a professor of computer science at Dartmouth College.
我是达特茅斯大学的一名计算机科学教授
Cormen 教授将与我们谈论所谓“初学者的革命”
Professor Cormen spoke with us about that beginner's revolution
以及 BASIC 的出现如何成为时代精神的一部分
and how the creation of BASIC really did feel like part of a new zeitgeist
它带来了一个新世界 在其中
a world where
计算机技术对更多人来说不仅不再遥不可及 甚至还是激动人心的
computing was exciting to more people,
- 编程甚至变得有点时髦了
even a little bit hip.
据说在 60 年代
At the time in the 1960s,
男学生会在这里（计算机中心）约会
it said that the male students would bring their dates there.
我真是不能想象如果发生在现在会是什么样子
I can't really imagine that happening now,
但在那个时候 计算机中心一度是约会的最佳场所
but at the time the computer center was the cool place to be.
这种在校园兴起的编程热潮
This new interest in computing on campus
是“初学者语言”诞生所带来的直接结果
was the immediate result of that first beginner's language.
BASIC 为那些计算机爱好者降低了准入门槛
BASIC opened up computing to people who weren't just computer jocks,
就如同我们过去说的那样
as we used to say back then.
不想学习 FORTRAN 这类编程语言的社会科学家
Social scientists who really didn't want to get into the weeds of a language like Fortran
可以使用 BASIC
could use BASIC.
从事人文艺术的人们
and people doing work in the arts and humanities
可以用它做文本处理 甚至用来创作艺术作品
if they were doing text analysis or even trying to create art
这些完全可以用 BASIC 来完成
they could use BASIC for that.
没过几年 人们就开始写电脑游戏
So after a few years, people were doing things like writing computer games
也时常在编程中实现图形化的内容
and also incorporating computer graphics routinely into their work.
对于所有那些不将自己视为程序员的孩子们
All those kids who didn't necessarily see themselves as programmers
编程领域的大门 突然间以一种近乎直观的方式打开了
suddenly got into programming on an almost intuitive level.
它让我想起格蕾丝·赫柏所追求的世界
It reminds me of the kind of world Grace Hopper pushed for.
当我们上一季谈到赫柏时
When we talked about Hopper last season,
我们谈到了她的语言创新如何将编程带到更多人眼前
we saw how her language innovations brought programming to a wider circle.
BASIC 的此时此刻就像是赫柏梦想的延续
This BASIC moment, it was like a continuation of Hopper's dream.
我非常确信 如果格蕾丝·赫柏能看到更多人开始写代码
I'm sure Grace Hopper would have liked seeing more people coding.
她会非常高兴
她可能会喜欢 BASIC 和 COBOL 的不同之处
She probably would have liked that BASIC had a different slant from COBOL
因为这种不同为人们提供了更多的选择
and that it just opened things up to people even more and gave them a choice.
他们可以写 COBOL 可以写 FORTRAN
They could write in COBOL, they could write in Fortran,
可以写 BASIC 可以写 ALGOL
they could write in BASIC, they could write in ALGOL
可以选择当时任何流行的语言
any of the popular languages of the time.
Tom Cormen 是达特茅斯计算机科学系的一名教授
Tom Cormen is a professor in Dartmouth's Computer Science Department.
当初 计算机技术中的几大变化催生了新一代的程序员
So a new generation of computer programmers was ushered in
thanks to a couple of major changes
分时功能使并行工作成为可能 而 BASIC 使入门编程变得简单了
simultaneous work made possible by time sharing, and a new simple language, BASIC.
这两个因素结合在一起 创造出了改变游戏规则的星星之火
Those two factors combined to create a game-changing spark.
很快 编程就不仅是大型机构的专利
Soon, it wasn't just massive institutions that could get into programming
这一代程序员中
it was mavericks, like Bill Gates and Steve Wozniak.
既有像比尔·盖茨和史蒂夫·沃兹尼亚克这样的特立独行者
也有在个人电脑上每天默默耕耘的开发者
It was also everyday programmers just exploring on their personal computers.
BASIC 能够在程序出错时立即给使用者以反馈
To be able to interact with a language to get immediate feedback when something was wrong
这让它的使用体验变得不同 它让你沉浸其中 使你继续前进
that made all the difference in the world because it sucked you in, it kept you going
这种交互是有意义的 就因为它是一种交互
and the interaction was meaningful because it was an interaction.
这位是 Denise Dumas 她带领 RHEL 工程师团队
This is Denise Dumas. She runs the Red Hat Enterprise Linux Engineering Team.
我认为 BASIC 使编程变得民主了许多
I mean, BASIC democratized programming in a big way, right?
因为 BASIC 把它自身交予学生、大众
Because it put it in the hands of students, in the hands of people
当时的其他语言 - 像是 COBOL、FORTRAN 之类
in a way that COBAL, Fortran, the other languages of the day,
- 根本做不到这一点
it just wasn't possible.
当 CRT（阴极射线管显示器）流行的时候 BASIC 更为火爆
It became really popular at a time when CRTs became popular.
因为在你输入了信息之后 输出不再是被打印在一张纸上
And so instead of typing something in and getting it printed on a piece of paper
而是显示在你面前的屏幕上
it displayed on a screen in front of you.
我们现在有时候会嘲笑命令行 对吧？
We laugh at command lines sometimes now, right?
现在一切都图形化了 但当时 有命令行已经很好了
Everything is graphics, but the command line was what there was.
它比命令行之前的时代有了很大的改进
And it was such an improvement over what had been.
这一重大改进就是 你输入指令能够立即得到回应了
That was huge. Just to type something in and get a response.
我认为 BASIC 降低了准入门槛
I think that BASIC lowered the bar.
虽然我是那种控制狂 我喜欢汇编 但我还是会这么说的
And I say this as someone who actually loves assembler
because that's the kind of control freak I am
BASIC 使编程变得更加平易近人
but I think BASIC made it much more approachable.
BASIC 在 1980 年代带来的这份激情一直延续到了今日
The excitement BASIC created in the 1980s lives on today.
现在 有许多语言
With a whole fleet of languages
能被初学者用作进入编程世界的光明大道
that beginners use as shiny red doors into the world of programming.
但如今发生了另一些重要的改变：
And yet something important has changed.
编程入门不再只有进入大学学习一途
Because those entrances don't just show up on university campuses anymore.
今日 条条大路通罗马
The way into programming is becoming even more open.
尽管 BASIC 很神奇 但格蕾丝·赫柏的梦想不会止步于此
As amazing as BASIC was, Grace Hopper's dream wasn't going to stop there.
如今 初学者有上百种方法可以开始编程
Today, beginners have a hundred ways to find their start.
就我而言
And for me, learning a first language
我是在纽约市一家名为 Flatiron 的学校学习的第一门语言
meant attending an institution called the Flatiron School in New York City.
我为那个项目准备了几个月
I prepared for months for that program.
我阅读了所有可能的编程资源和教程
I read every single programming resource and tutorial
以确保它们也许能让我在训练营中获得最大收益
that I possibly could to make sure I got the most out of my boot camp.
我想了解当今人们是如何接触自己的入门语言的
I wanted to learn about how people today discovered that first language.
所以 今天我采访了自己当初的那位老师
So I headed back to interview my old teacher.
我是 Avi Flombaum
I'm Avi Flombaum.
Avi 是 Flatiron 学校的创始人之一
Avi is one of the founders of the Flatiron School.
对我来说 和他一起探究有关入门语言的思想
So it was a treat for me to dig into Avi's thoughts about first languages.
和我们接触入门语言的方式
And how our approaches to first languages
与 BASIC 的旧时代相比有什么变化 是一种享受
have changed since the old days of BASIC.
当你教别人该如何编程时 先从哪里下手呢？
So when you are teaching someone how to code, where do you begin?
我记得当我学习第一门编程语言时
Because I remember when I first learned my first programming language
我觉得这一切可真是太奇怪了
thinking, this is so weird.
我在大学读的是英语专业 在学校里我很喜欢数学
You know, I was an English major. I really liked maths when I was in school.
也喜欢有机化学
I liked organic chemistry.
我喜欢很多不同的科目 各种各样的东西
There are a lot of things that I was really into, a lot of different subjects.
但是没有什么是和编程相似的
But there was nothing I could connect coding to.
因此 我也没办法将编程比作什么
There was nothing that was a good analogy.
它自成一套 就像一个自己的小世界
You know, it just felt like its own little world.
所以 作为老师 你会从哪里开始呢
So as a teacher, where do you start?
我认为生活中你所熟悉的任何事物 曾经都是陌生的
I think that anything that is familiar to you in life was once foreign
只有经历过
and experiencing it and, you know,
真正花时间去做
waiting in its waters and actually spending time with it
才会让你对它感到习惯
is what makes you comfortable with it.
这是不断重复练习的问题 只关乎你投入的时间的多少
And it's just a question of reps and really just time that you put into it.
我认为编程之所以困难 之所以让人感觉如此陌生
I think what makes programming difficult and what makes it feel so foreign
是因为它用极其特殊的语法来表达一些东西
is that it is a tremendously particular syntax for expressing something.
没有任何歧义 没有错误的余地 要么成功 要么失败
There's zero ambiguity. There's no margin of error. It either works or it doesn't.
当我们互相交流的时候
And when we communicate to each other,
我们一般没有那种要求
we generally don't have that kind of requirement
一切都必须完全正确
where everything has to be exactly correct.
一个逗号丢了 一个括号缺了 就全坏了
You know, one comma is off, one parenthesis missing and just it's all broken.
我总是说 计算机是愚蠢的
I always say that computers are stupid
为了使计算机理解我们的意思 我们必须做到完美
and we have to just be perfect in order to get them understand what we mean.
这个我喜欢 机器是笨蛋
I like that. I like this idea of the machine being the stupid one
我比它聪明 我同意
and me being the smart one. I approve of this. This is great.
是啊
Yeah.
我的第一门编程语言是 Ruby
For me, that first language, the one I cut my teeth on, was Ruby.
根据经验 我可以告诉你 这是一种非常可爱的入门语言
From experience, I can tell you it's a pretty sweet first language.
当你阅读代码时 感觉就像你在阅读英语
When you read the code, it feels like you're reading English.
它有很多不错的库
It's got tons of great libraries.
这里插播一则知识补充
And here's a bit of trivia.
Ruby 的创造者 松本行弘
The creator of Ruby, Yukihiro Matsumoto,
是通过学习 BASIC 进入编程领域的
he got into programming by learning BASIC.
如今 许多新手可能会改用 Python 或 JavaScript
These days, a lot of newbies might be tackling Python or JavaScript instead.
而我想知道 Avi 你觉得
And I wanted to know whether Avi thought
有没有最理想的入门语言
any one language was a better front door than all the others.
我想知道 是否有首选的入门语言？
I'm wondering, are there preferred starter languages?
如果某人没有技术背景
If someone's coming into this with no tech background,
没有编程经验 也没有计算机科学学历而进入这个领域
no coding experience, no CS degree,
那么他们就是从一开始 甚至说从零开始…
they're starting from absolutely nothing from square one, square zero even.
随着时间的推移 有没有更好的初始语言冒出来呢？
Are there preferred languages that are good starting points that have changed over time?
首先 我要说的是每个人都没有背景
Well, first, I'll say that everyone comes into it with no background.
没有谁生下来就是程序员
No one is born a programmer.
因此 无论你是有计算机科学学历
So whether you formally learned it in a CS program
还是在社区中心里学习 抑或读书自学
or in your community center or read books and taught yourself,
每个人都是从初学者开始的
everyone started as a beginner.
然后 就初学者的首选语言而言
And then in terms of the preferred beginner language,
我认为你最先看到的语言就是最好的
I think it's really whatever speaks to you first.
我对初学者的建议始终是 选择一种语言并学习它 不要改变
My advice to beginners is always just pick a language and learn it. Don't change.
我认为 初学者最容易犯的错是
I think the biggest thing that beginners do is
我先学习 Python 遭了挫折
start learning Python and then get frustrated with it
就说 Python 很烂 现在我要去用 JavaScript 了
and say Python sucks and now I'm going to go do JavaScript.
他们学习 JavaScript 然后对 JavaScript 感到沮丧
And then they learn JavaScript and then they get frustrated with JavaScript
然后又换了起来
and then they jump again.
如你所知 我个人认为 Ruby 是一种很棒的初学者语言
I personally, as you know, think that Ruby is a great beginner language.
我认为它的语法真的很漂亮
I think that its syntax is just really beautiful.
它的理念 明确地就是要使你（程序员）感到高兴
Its value explicitly is to make you the programmer happy.
我不知道是否有其他发明来就是要叫程序员开心的语言
I don't know any other language that was invented to make a programmer happy.
我知道人们发明了许多语言来使机器开心
I know a lot of languages are invented to make machines happy.
但我认为 Ruby 确实很自然
But I think Ruby is really natural.
这一点我们可以达成共识 但是同样 这里没有错误的答案
We can agree on that one. But again, there's no wrong answer here.
毕竟 入门语言就是这样
A first language after all is just that.
它只是开始 我们所有人都有一生的时间用来学习
A first. We've all got a whole lifetime of language learning ahead of us.
而且 选择一种语言而不是另一种语言
And besides, choosing one language over another
并不会阻止你成为出色的程序员
isn't going to stop you from becoming the awesome programmer you were destined to be.
我喜欢画画 但我不会为了一支笔而死去活来
You know, I like to draw, but I will not live and die by a particular pen.
我不会因为我使用的笔而大动干戈
You know, like I don't get all worked up over the pen that I use.
我为我所创造的东西而激动
I get worked up over the things I create.
那么从你的经验来看 为什么会这样呢？
And so from your experience, where does that come from?
在大家面前辩护 让大家相信
Where does that need to defend and convince everyone
你对一种编程语言的看法是正确的
that you were right about a programming language?
这样的一种思维是从何而来的呢？
Where does that come from?
我也不知道
I guess, I don't know.
因为我很喜欢你关于笔与作品的比喻 我首先想到的是…
The first thing that came into my head,
because I loved your metaphor of the pen versus the output.
在我的设想中 人们死死地抓住工具
I just imagine that some of the output is not that great.
恐怕是因为作品并不吸引人
So the only thing that people can hold on to is the tool.
这就很好笑了
That's hilarious.
如果你做的东西就是不厉害 不伟大
If the things you make just aren't awesome and aren't great
对这个世界也没有太大的价值
and don't have a lot of value for the world
你还想捍卫你的手艺
and you want to still defend your craft,
你唯一能指出的就是 是啊 看我把那把锤子挥得多好
the only thing you can point to is like, yeah, but look how well I swung that hammer.
当然 房子虽然倒了
Sure, the house fell apart,
但那把锤子 那把锤子真的很棒 我知道怎么用
but that hammer, that hammer is really great and I know how to use it.
你知道
And you know,
我这个人…我也觉得建造出的东西
as someone like, I always was more interested in the things I built
比你建造它的方式更重要
than the manner in which I built them.
说得好
That's a good point.
现在 初学者不止可以选择 BASIC 或者 FORTRAN
Now that beginners have more to choose from
than just BASIC or, I don't know, Fortran,
我们已经拥有一整套的入门语言清单
now that we have a whole menu of first languages,
但总有一种危险
there's always the danger
那就是你忘记了这些语言仍然是达到目的的一种手段
that you forget these languages are still a means to an end.
语言是工具 不是你要制作的东西
The language is the tool. It's not the thing you're making.
我认为技术的价值在于 为人们创造有意义的事物
I think that the value of technology is to create meaningful things for people.
说到底 如果你确实是一名非常非常好的程序员
Ultimately, if you're a programmer and you're really, really good,
但是你做的东西没有人需要 没有人喜欢…
but you're building things that no one needs and no one likes and, you know
它没有为世界增加价值
aren't adding value to the world,
但是你真的真的非常擅长这门手艺
but you're really, really good at the craft
我想你可能会深入研究并讨论所使用的工具
and you just can't find a way to actually make the impact you want.
I imagine that you'd probably dig in and talk about the tool you used.
非常感谢 Avi
Well, thank you so much, Avi,
感谢你分享你的所有经验以及对编程语言的想法
for sharing all your experiences and your thoughts about programming languages.
那我们就谈到这里？
You want to say goodbye?
是的 这非常好玩 很高兴再次跟你交流
Yeah, this was super fun. It was nice connecting again.
我希望大家都找到自己喜欢的语言 每天都能用它写代码
And I hope you all find a language that you love and get to work in it every day.
听起来不错
Sounds good.
Avi Flombaum 是 Flatiron 学校的联合创始人之一
Avi Flombaum is one of the co-founders of Flatiron School.
编程学校可以将教育和知识获取的精神提升到一个全新的高度
Coding schools can bring that spirit of access and education to a whole new level.
这是我们在达特茅斯看到的一切的延续
It's a continuation of what we saw at Dartmouth.
但如今 在一个多样化的开发生态系统中
But in a rich development ecosystem,
新的、更加自然的入门方式将会不断涌现
we'll keep getting more and more natural points of entry.
初学者们已经有了更理想的手段来开始他们的编程“游戏”
And first-time coders are already discovering next-level ways to get into the game.
有时 他们甚至真是从玩游戏开始的
Sometimes, literally.
你试过其他键吗？试试 G 键
Have you tried like a different key? So, why don't you try the G key?
现在 在这暂停
Now, hold on.
这不是一群年轻的程序员在默默地背诵 O'Reilly 的课本
That is not a bunch of young coders silently memorizing an O'Reilly textbook.
也不是在 Flatiron 学校的讲座
And it's not a lecture at the Flatiron School either.
这其实是红帽在伦敦泰特现代美术馆里开办的一节实践课
It's actually a little lab that Red Hat ran at the Tate Modern in London.
那些孩子呢？他们在学习写代码
And those kids, they're learning to code.
对于新一代来说 编程的乐趣就是他们首先体会到的
For a new generation, the joy of coding is what they first encounter.
好的 嗨 我叫 Femi 网名是 Hackerfemo
Okay. Hi, my name is Femi, aka Hackerfemo.
大家可以在 Github 找到他的账号 不过他这两年好像没怎么活动 :(
Femi Owolade-Coombes 只有 13 岁
Femi Owolade-Coombes is only 13 years old,
但他已经是新一代程序员中的一名领袖
but he's already a leader in a new wave of young coders.
我八岁的时候第一次接触到编程
I first encountered coding when I was eight,
那时我去约克参加一项活动 活动本身其实是数学主题的
and I went to an event in York, actually, about maths.
不过我在那里看到了个很酷的东西 - 合法地黑入 Minecraft
And there, I saw this cool thing, you know, hacking Minecraft, ethically.
作为八岁的孩子 那时候的我认为那真的很酷
And as an eight-year-old, I thought that was really cool.
所以我就这样入门了编程
So that's how I got into coding.
他不是孤例 Minecraft 已经将一代人引入了编程领域
He's not alone. Minecraft has introduced a whole generation to coding.
而且这不需要过去几代人所经历的痛苦和枯燥的学习
And it's done that without any of the pain or dry studying
that past generations suffered through.
游戏的魔力正在消除障碍
The magic of gaming is dropping barriers.
Minecraft 是基于 Java 的
Minecraft is Java-based,
它也为该语言注入了新的活力
and it's been credited with breathing new life into that language
催生了一大群新的 Java 粉丝
spawning a whole crowd of fresh-faced Java fans.
但不一定是 Java
But it doesn't have to be Java.
对于 Femi来 说 Python 是他在 Minecraft 中发现的语言
For Femi, Python was the language he discovered in Minecraft.
如果你玩的是树莓派版的 Minecraft 你就可以用 Python
You can use Python when you're using the Raspberry Pi in Minecraft
因为树莓派上的 Minecraft 是特殊编写的版本 它很酷
because Minecraft have created a special edition for the Raspberry Pi, which is so cool
只要导入这个库 你就可以黑进去
because you can hack it by just importing this, like, library,
到处放置爆炸性的 TNT
and you can put exploding TNT everywhere.
你可以在自己身后创建方块
And you can create blocks behind you.
也可以创造建筑物 你可以拿它做各种各样的事
You can create whole buildings, all sorts of things.
当我第一次玩它时 我发现可以添加很多类似 mod 的东西
When I first played it, I knew there were quite a few things like mods you could add on,
这也很酷
which are pretty cool.
mod 这东西本身就有点像黑进游戏一样
Those were like little hacks in themselves.
但 mod 的存在让我意识到
But this was the first time that I realized you could, like,
我们也可以用正规的方法改变游戏 让它以你希望的方式行事
properly hack it and really make it do what you want.
我认为这真的很酷
I thought it was really cool.
Femi 打开了一个编程世界
A world of coding opened up for Femi,
而通往世界的大门是他最喜欢的游戏
and the door to that world was his favorite game.
然后 他做了一件了不起的事情
And then Femi did something kind of amazing.
他开始向其他孩子分享那扇门
He started showing other kids that door.
嗯 我想与同伴分享我的知识
Well, I wanted to share my knowledge with my peers,
因为我觉得 你知道吗？他们会非常喜欢的
because I thought, you know what, they will really enjoy this.
我也会因此度过愉快的时光
And I have, and I had a great time,
我想与其他所有人共享这些 这样他们就能了解它
I want to share this with everyone else, so that they can learn about it
甚至可以参与编程
and so that they can even get into coding.
Femi 将此事贯彻到底 创办了“南伦敦树莓酱”社团
Femi went ahead and founded the South London Raspberry Jam.
Jam 有即兴演奏的意思
在那里 他已经看到了全新一代的编程者
And there, he's been able to watch a whole new generation of coders
他们正挑战人们以往对编程初体验的预判
defy expectations about what a first language experience should look like.
除了“黑进 Minecraft”之外
Besides those Minecraft hacks,
像 Scratch 或 Fruit 这样的可视化语言
visual languages like Scratch or Fruit
也让越来越年轻的用户拥有基础知识可以实现编程
are making the basics of coding achievable to younger and younger users.
我确实喜欢玩游戏这个点子
I do like the idea of playing a game,
比起在课堂上学习代码 我肯定更想在游戏里学习
and I most certainly do it over, you know, learning to code in a classroom.
我最喜欢的是能够控制游戏中发生的事情
But it's the idea of, you know, being able to control what happens in that game.
而代码是背后的魔法
And code is behind that,
代码给了你那种非常酷的能力 让游戏做你想要的事情
and code gives you that really cool ability to make the game do what you want.
Femi 的妈妈告诉我们
Femi's mom told us how happy she was
当她发现玩游戏并非一种弊大于利的追求时 她有多么高兴
to discover that gaming didn't have to be a passive pursuit.
我喜欢他的故事 因为这故事是从游戏开始的 却没有结束于游戏
What I love about his story is that it starts with gaming, sure, but it doesn't end there.
他建立了一个属于年轻程序员的、了不起的社区
He built an amazing community of young coders,
Femi 自己的代码生涯也在起飞
and Femi's own coding life is taking off.
不再是围绕着 Minecraft 了
It's not just Minecraft anymore.
他学会了使用 HTML、JavaScript 和 CSS
He works in HTML, JavaScript and CSS,
建立网站 做网页设计
building websites and doing Web design.
他甚至在用 Unity 打造自己的游戏
He's even building his own games using Unity.
每个人都应该有权利学习编程 因为这是未来
Everyone really should have a right to learn how to code because it is the future.
Minecraft 真的是一所巨型编程大学吗？
So is Minecraft really a giant programming university?
明日的程序员 是否会通过游戏和玩耍来吸收新的语言呢？
Are the coders of tomorrow going to absorb new languages
through games and simply messing around?
只通过环境渗透能否真正地学习语言？
Will languages be learned just through osmosis?
嗨 我叫 Robyn Bergeron
Hi, my name is Robyn Bergeron.
是第二季番外篇请到过的人:)
Robyn 是红帽的 Ansible 社区架构师
Robyn's the community architect for Ansible over at Red Hat.
她有几个孩子
And she also happens to have a couple kids
这些孩子们偶然间接触到了编程
who've stumbled into programming themselves.
那是晚饭时刻
So there was a moment at dinner one night.
我在做饭
I was actually cooking.
每个人对这件事情都印象深刻
Everyone was impressed.
我的女儿来到厨房 她说:
My daughter came into the kitchen area and she said,
“妈妈 我给 Minecraft 提交了一个 bug！”
Mommy, I filed a bug in Minecraft.
我从事软件工作
You know, I work in software.
我看到过很多很多错误报告
I get to see lots, you know, lots and lots and lots of bug reports.
我真的很好奇 她这么讲究竟是什么意思
And I was just really curious about what that meant in that universe, right?
是说我在推特上和别人聊了聊 说它坏了 还是什么？
Is that like, you know, I've talked to someone on Twitter and said it's broken or what?
我让她给我看看
And I asked her to show me.
于是她打开了电脑
So she opened up, you know, her computer
她已经在 Mojang 的系统中创建了一个 Jira 帐户
and she had created a Jira account in Mojang system.
我们应该注意到 Robyn 的女儿在当时只有 11 岁
We should note Robyn's daughter was 11 when she did this.
她把表格填得像模像样
She had filled out their form exactly.
我见过很多内容不完整的错误报告
And, you know, I see lots of bug reports that are not well formed
也见过很多口吻过于尖锐的错误报告
or they're very mean. I see a lot of that too.
但这是一个完美的报告…这份报告里有说“发生了什么事”
But it was a perfectly, you know, here's what happened.
“我预期会发生什么事”
Here's what I expected to happen.
以及“如何重现错误”
And here's all of the steps to reproduce,
对于很多人来说 这是他们与项目的第一次互动
which is, you know, for a lot of people that's their first interaction with any project,
无论是商业的
whether it's a, you know, commercial
专有的软件项目 比如一个电子游戏
you know, proprietary software project like a video game
还是一个开源软件项目
or a open source software project.
我很自豪
And I was so proud.
我告诉她 之后我们完全可以去参加 Minecraft 大会
And I told her we could totally go to the Minecraft conference after that
因为他们一直很想去
because they had been dying to go.
Robyn 意识到 当我们其他人从事日常工作时
Robyn was about to realize that while the rest of us were going about our day jobs
孩子们却开始了一场革命
the kids were starting a revolution.
以下是在那场 Minecraft 大会上发生的事情
Here's what happened at that conference.
我们去参加主题演讲 我说 就算我们排在最后进去也没事的
We went to the keynotes and I said, oh, we'll go at the last second.
会在第二排找到位置
We'll be fine.
We'll totally be like in the second row.
完全错了
Oh, no.
大错特错
No, no, no.
我们坐得就跟房间后面那 10 个大屏幕一样靠后
We were like 10 of those gigantic big screens back in the room.
不过这并没有减少孩子们的热情
But it was nonstop cool stuff for kids.
大会的其中一天 全体开发人员也出场了 这可把孩子们激动坏了
And they had a moment on one of the days where they brought out all of the developers.
当工程师们出来的时候
And when the engineers came out,
所有在场的孩子都站起来尖叫
literally every kid in this audience was like standing on their chair screaming.
如果你看过披头士乐队表演的视频
Like if you've ever seen a, here's the Beatles,
那时候就像披头士乐队来美国时一样
like the Beatles come to America video.
It was like that.
粉丝们就好像是“我没办法相信 他们就在我们眼前 他们太棒了”
I mean, it was like, I can't believe we're like near them and they're amazing.
在讲演期间
And, you know, during the sessions,
人们都在试图得到他们的签名
people were trying to get their autographs and it was,
这是…我和我的孩子坐在那里
you know, I'm sitting there with my kids being like
我在想 我开发操作系统 连接互联网
I work on operating systems that connect the Internet
这样你们才能在一起玩游戏吧？
so that you guys can actually game together.
我们做错了什么 才会如此默默无闻呢？
What are we doing wrong?
但是孩子们就像
But, you know, kids are just being like,
我长大后要成为使用 JavaScript 的人！
I'm going to be a JavaScript person when I grow up.
Yes.
是的 那个活动带来的热烈氛围令人着迷
And, you know, just watching the level of enthusiasm at that event was fascinating.
但…这是一个电子游戏
But it's a video game.
在 70 年代的某一段时间
There was a time back in the seventies
每个人的入门语言都是 BASIC
when everyone's first language was BASIC.
然后可能是 C
And then maybe it was C.
近来 人们开始使用 Java 或 Python
More recently, people have been starting with Java or Python.
但是可视化语言编程和游戏
But visual languages and games
正在催生我们鲜有设想的编程未来
are ushering in a coding future that we're only beginning to imagine.
尽管对于已经从事多年编程工作的人来说 这似乎微不足道
Even though it may seem trivial to someone who's been programming for years,
但我开始游玩的那一刻
it's, you know, like that first moment of, I'm playing.
我甚至没有意识到 我其实是在学习一种
And I don't even realize that I'm actually learning something
可以让我受益终生的东西
that could turn into a lifelong skill.
Robyn Bergeron 是红帽的 Ansible 社区架构师
Robyn Bergeron is the community architect of Ansible at Red Hat.
BASIC 邀请大学生进入编程世界
BASIC invited college students into the world of programming.
而 Minecraft 等游戏则邀请小学生进入当今的编程世界
And games like Minecraft invite elementary school students into that world today.
但是从某种意义上说 创造的动力并没有改变
But in a way, the creative impulse behind all of this hasn't changed.
那些大学生在学习 BASIC？
Those college kids exploring BASIC.
是的 他们经常用它来编写游戏
Yeah, they were often using it to build their own games.
最常见的似乎是足球题材
Lots of fantasy football, apparently.
创新精神是驱使我们学习编程语言的第一推动力
Our creative spirit is what drives us toward programming languages in the first place.
这种驱动力让我们使世界变得更好 或变得更加有趣
That drive to tweak the world, make it better or just more fun.
下次 在第 3 集中
Next time in episode three,
我们会讲述 全新的编程语言究竟从何而来？
where do brand new programming languages come from anyway?
我们会了解到 巨大挑战
We're learning how incredible challenges
是如何推动着开发人员从过去的语言中走出来
push developers to walk away from the languages of yesterday
并在今天创造出新事物的
and build something totally new today.
《代码英雄》是红帽出品的原创播客
Command Line Heroes is an original podcast from Red Hat.
如果你想更深入地了解 BASIC 的起源
If you want to dive deeper into the origins of BASIC
或在本集中听到的其他内容
or anything else you heard on this episode,
请转至 redhat.com/commandlineheroes
head on over to to redhat.com/commandlineheroes.
我是 Saron Yitbarek
I'm Saron Yitbarek. Until next time, keep on coding.
在下期节目到来之前 也请继续编程